Gianmaria Del Monte

SOFTWARE ENGINEER

Geneva - Switzerland

 ¶ +41 078 225 24 27
 |
 ■ gianmaria.del.monte@cern.ch
 |
 • github.com/gmgigi96

in linkedin.com/in/gianmaria-del-monte-81575b162



Personal Profile

Diligent Software Engineer with passion of designing and developing **highly scalable software systems**. Excellent attention to details and problem solving, with an innate ability to learn and master new technologies. Experience in software development's life cycle, including **designing**, **coding**, **testing**, **delivery** and **maintenance**. Keen to use my skills to push the frontiers of science and technology.

Work Experience

CERN Geneva, Switzerland

DevOps Storage Engineer for CERNBox (Fellowship)

Jan 2021 - Present

My main responsibility as a member of the agile CERNBox/EOS DevOps team is to lead the development, operation and release to production of the CERNBox server component, a critical asset for the delivery of the service that provides cloud storage for more than 37,000 CERN user accounts and 30 LHC and non-LHC experiments. I use Configuration Management and Infrastructure Automation with Puppet, following CERN IT best practices to operate the infrastructure (OpenStack, Monitoring, Databases) required to deliver the service at the established service level agreement. Part of my job is to also diagnose and optimize Linux Operating Systems (CentOS7, CentOS Stream 8 and Alma9), filesystems (FUSE), targeting the requirements of interested groups and experiments: speed, reliability, and cost. I proactively help to develop and operate the set interested in the laboratory's needs

- Coordinating the releases of the CERNBox server and backup software to the wide user population so they gain maximum benefit from the service
- · Carrying out day-day to operations in a timely and reliable manner (reacting to alarms and performing maintenance tasks)
- Designing and providing meaningful integrations with other data management services (for example, backup with Ceph, cback with CTA, CERN-Box with ScienceMesh)
- Leading the software development of different projects (Reva and cback) in different programming languages (Go, Python)
- Showing flexibility to accommodate rapid requirement changes (bugfixes and outages)
- Resolving incidents and problems, including classification, prioritization, initiating action, documentation of root causes, implementation of remedies and escalating them appropriately
- Improving existing procedures and created new ones to augment the service knowledge base
- Automating repetitive tasks to optimize the support ROTA and maintenance operations (cernboxcop)
- · Scoping and installing new machines (VM, docker) for supporting the growing needs of the service
- Improving the awareness of the service by providing new monitoring data and better testing probes (new CERNBox SLS probes and new metrics systems for cback)
- · Performing interventions on critical components during out-of-working hours and holiday periods
- Developing support tools for enhanced operations using shell programming (Python, Shell)
- Troubleshooting and debugging anomalies in distributed storage systems, especially EOS (CERN large-scale disk system, with more than 50,000 disk across 16,000 servers) over different low-level transport protocols (wire, GRPC, HTTP)
- Tuning and optimizing Linux storage device drivers (FUSE on restic)
- Performing deep-dive investigations across massive amounts of logging data and metrics (EOS logs)

CERN Geneva, Switzerland

2nd line Computer Security Response (ROTA)

May 2022 - Present

My main responsibility as a member of the CERN IT Security ROTA is to help with my skills to mitigate the cybersecurity threats to the laboratory and aissing mythodifferent to pitroites identification to the laboratory and aissing mythodifferent to pitroites identified and account to the laboratory and aissing mythodifferent to pitroites identified and account to the laboratory and aissing mythodifferent to pitroites identified and account to the laboratory and account to the labor

- Managed security alerts, incident reports, and user inquiries ensuring timely response and resolution
- Validating changes to CERN's outer perimeter firewall and authorizing configuration after successful penetration tests, contributing to the overall security infrastructure

Education

MEDILS Split, Croatia

Thematic CERN School of Computing

• Held on Security of research computing infrastructures

2022

1

Rome Tre University Rome, Italy

M.Sc. in Computer Engineering

- Thesis title: Scaling blockchains without giving up decentralization and security
- Thesis supervisor: Prof. Maurizio Pizzonia
- Final mark: 110/110 with honors

Rome Tre University Rome, Italy

B.Sc. in Computer Engineering

2016 - 2018

2019 - 2020

- Thesis title: Implementation of an efficient protocol for data integrity on Cloud storage systems
- Thesis supervisor: Prof. Maurizio Pizzonia
- Final mark: 110/110 with honors

Skills_

Programming Go, Python, C

Miscellaneous Linux, Shell (Bash/Zsh), Git, MySQL, PostgreSQL, Redis, MongoDB, Puppet, Foreman, Grafana, Docker, Distributed storage systems

(EOS), distribute programming, desing patterns, design architectures

Soft Skills Time Management, teamwork, problem solving, communication, positive attitude, self-supervising, team leadership, flexibility

Achievements_

2019	3rd place , Local competitions of CyberChallenge 2019	Italy
2019	4th place, National competitions of CyberChallenge 2019	Italy
2018	Elite, Luca Raso scholarship for best students enrolled in Master's degree in Computer Engineering at Roma	Italy
2010	Tre University.	naiy
2016	Winner, Scholarship for best average grade in the Engineering Department of Roma Tre University.	Italy

Publications

Scaling blockchains without giving up decentralization and security: A solution to the blockchain scalability trilemma Gianmaria Del Monte, Diego Pennino, Maurizio Pizzonia

Proceedings of the 3rd Workshop on Cryptocurrencies and Blockchains for Distributed Systems, 2020

Conferences

 $\hbox{C(ERN) BACK(UP): consolidated multi-petabyte backup solution for heterogenous storage and file systems} \\$

Gianmaria Del Monte, Elizaveta Ragozina, Roberto Valverde Cameselle

 $CS3\,2023-Cloud\,Storage\,Synchronization\,and\,Sharing,\,2023, \\ \textbf{https://indico.cern.ch/event/1210538/contributions/5207944}$

Applications integration beyond local clouds with OCM

Giuseppe Lo Presti, Gianmaria Del Monte, Michiel De Jong

 $\textit{CS3 2023 - Cloud Storage Synchronization and Sharing, 2023, \texttt{https://indico.cern.ch/event/1210538/contributions/5206694} \\$

Evolution of the CERN Backup system based on RESTIC and the CERN Tape Archive (CTA)

Fons Rademakers, Gianmaria Del Monte

26TH INTERNATIONAL CONFERENCE ON COMPUTING IN HIGH ENERGY AND NUCLEAR PHYSICS - CHEP2023, 2023, https://indico.jlab.org/event/459/contributions/11294/

User-friendly OCM Invitation and Sharing: OCIS, CERNBox

Elizaveta Ragozina, Gianmaria Del Monte, Samuel Alfageme Sainz

CS3 2023 - Cloud Storage Synchronization and Sharing, 2023, https://indico.cern.ch/event/1210538/contributions/5208014

CERNBox backup evolution

Gianmaria Del Monte, Roberto Valverde Cameselle

6th EOS workshop, 2022, https://indico.cern.ch/event/1103358/contributions/4758282

Data safety in CERNBox

Gianmaria Del Monte

CERNBox User Forum, 2021, https://indico.cern.ch/event/1067354/contributions/4646494/

Visualizing physics data in ownCloud Infinite Scale

Gianmaria Del Monte

ownCloud Conference, 2021, https://cfp.owncloud.com/occon2021/talk/W8KHKM

Languages _____

EnglishProfessional proficiencyItalianNative proficiencyFrenchBasic knowledge